Hello everyone.
Can everyone hear me?
OK?
OK, cool.
Yeah.
Welcome to Day 2 of Build, I guess.
How has day 2 been going for everyone so far?
Good, good.
Cool.
Yeah, yeah.
Like I was introduced, I'm a software engineering manager on
the Foundry of the Ability team, and I'm excited to
share with you today how you can run consistent, high
quality and actionable agent observability in Foundry no matter what
agent framework you use or whether your agents are running.
OK, quick show of hands.
How many of you build or operate agents in production?
OK, cool, some of you.
And so keep your hands up if all of the
agents, like either your agents or your team agents are
running on the same cloud provider using the same programming
language and same agent framework, anyone OK, I guess 1
lucky person there.
OK, So what we hear from customers again and again
is that the production reality is that big companies like
enterprise companies, they really have this heterogeneous agent set up
right like that.
You mean, you know, like maybe a sorry, so maybe
a product team, you know, like they picked foundries, prompt
agents because it's easier to iterate on the portal, right?
And then a back end team might picked up land
Graph and run it on AWS because land graph is
the agent framework they are most familiar with.
And the third team might have adopted ADK from Google
because they are already on GCP.
We're on Gemini, right?
And then all of a sudden maybe someone asks for
Copilot SDK as a catch all because that's a new
thing they have recently heard about.
And very quickly you run into this mess that, you
know, different agent framework, different hosting stack, different metrics and
different dashboard.
And then like all of a sudden maybe like a
bad response came up from your agentic system in production
and you are waiting to start to ask scary questions
like, oh, which agent did that?
Why did the agent return this bad answer?
And how do we prevent bad behaviors from happening in
the future, right?
Today I'm going to show you how to answer those
questions in one place.
Foundry observability.
Not by rewriting your agents into one agent framework, but
by adopting open AI, sorry, open telemetry instrumentation with a
few lines of code and without changing your existing agent
logic.
And everything we show in this demo are live and
available on Foundry.
You can check out the code and reproduce everything we
show with the repository we will share at the end
of the talk.
Let's start with a simple agent before bringing multi agent,
multi cloud setup.
OK, you guys can see this right?
OK, so if this is the first time you are
saying this, this is Microsoft Foundry portal and this is
a playground view that allow me to quickly configure and
test out my agents, right?
And the story here is that, you know, I grew
up in Xi'an, a famous tourist destination in China, and
often get asked by friends for travel recommendations.
So I went ahead and built a travel expert agent
with Foundry's no code offering called Prompt agent, right?
And what I did is that I picked a model
for my agent.
I gave it some judge prompt, sorry, system prompt.
And you know, it can be even like multi language
if you want.
And the secret sauce here is that I have this
kind of travel notes in PDF file, right?
With even pictures and different links and everything.
I uploaded it to the Foundry here as an index
so that my agent can access that travel notes when
it needs to.
OK, and I can send a question here.
For example, plan a three day trip in Xian for
two people.
Focus on history and the food you can see the
agent started to return detailed itinerary, which shouldn't be a
surprise today, right?
It calls out, you know, famous places to visit again
in multi languages and also restaurant recommendations, right.
We can take a closer look here again, like, you
know, three day, like day by day plan and like
with all the details calling out like interesting places, right?
But again, like we're in 2026, this shouldn't be a
surprise, right?
What's more interesting is that I can go to the
traces view to see like how the agent was able
to get to that answer, right?
Here is a list of all the previous conversations I've
had with this agent.
And like there are different dimensions you can see here,
like token cost, token in, token out, maybe estimated cost,
right?
And I can do sort and filtering if I want
to.
And maybe we can also like dig into a specific
trace.
OK, let's try a different one.
OK, Yeah, this is a good one.
And Foundry provides also this like clear view to allow
me to understand the behavior of my agents, right?
I can even maximize it a little bit at the
upper right corner.
It's a little bit small.
But I think these are key metrics about this conversation
like number of spans, number of chat calls, number of
tool calls, latency and token consumption, right?
So it's very clear those are the key metrics.
And if you look at this tree view, everything is
rooted under a single invoke agent spam that has the
system message, the input from the customer and the output
from the agent.
And following that is a executed tool spam that the
agent uses to look up my travel notes right?
If we look take a closer look at the metadata
tab here, we'll be able to see like, oh the
this is a query the agent used to retrieve content
from my PDF file, right?
And this is like the final answer the tool was
able to retrieve to give back to the agent.
This is kind of a classic RAG pattern if you
guys have heard about that and in case you know
like if the agent running into any hallucination problem or
groundliness problem, this is likely we will where I will
start my debugging from and eventually everything is fed into
an LM for the final answer.
You can see that we have a replay button here
that, you know, I can choose the speed if I
do this, you know, I see like how the agent
is actually being executed.
And if I go to the user view, I can
even experience what an end user will see from this
agent, right?
Pretty cool.
OK, yeah, this really gives me a very clear view
to help me to deeply understand my agent behavior and
debug issues when I need to, right.
And at this point, you might be wondering, does this
only come with Foundry native agents?
What about my agents running somewhere else, right?
Do I get the same experience?
To answer that question, let me bring in my colleague
like Kumar.
Hi, talk about that.
Hi, I'm Nak Kumar and what I did along with
Hanshi was to build a similar travel agent about the
place that I'm from Bangalore and I call it the
Bangalore travel agent.
Unlike Hanshi's agent, Mind runs on GCP using the Google,
Google's ADK, and after registering it on the Foundry as
an external agent, we'll get to see the same rich
trace experience that you saw earlier.
So this is my trace experience screen, and I can
click on a screen on a trace and then look
at the responses.
But while we do that, I want to also send
a request to my GCP agent via curl.
So you can see it's running on Run dot app,
which is DCP.
And then we can take a look at the response
as soon as it's up here.
Yeah.
So that we know this is a real agent running
on GCP, right?
We're not like picking anything.
Yeah, I guess it will take a little bit to
come back because of network.
OK, here it comes back.
Yeah, you can see the city there.
And what?
OK, like this is a real agent running on GCP,
right?
We were able to send the HP request and get
this response back.
And to make this even more interesting, because like Kumar
and I both live in Seattle currently, so we even
build a third agent for Seattle Travel Tips and we
have it using the land graph and running on AWS.
Yeah, so I'm doing the same thing, sending out a
call to my agent on AWS with a question about
Seattle.
And while this is running, I'll explain the whole magic
behind it.
We also built another agent which acts as an orchestrator.
And that agent was built with Microsoft found is deployed
on the Foundry as hosted agent and uses our Microsoft
agent framework.
The way it works is it routes intelligently based on
the city that you ask it to.
And then all of them would emit open telemetry traces.
We can.
Here's the difference for the Seattle agent, and we can
jump into showcasing how the trace looks like that.
Sounds great.
Let's do that.
So this is the same agent that I told you
about, the orchestrator that we have.
This is the one.
That will invoke multiple agents across multiple.
Clouds, right?
Yep.
And if you see my message, I'm asking about Seattle,
Bangalore and Lisbon.
Lisbon is not one of the countries that we built
an agent for.
So there is a copilot SDK which acts as a
fall back for cities that we don't have data about
or we don't have like a specialized agent for.
While this is running, I can head on over to
the traces tab and show you an open trace from
earlier.
So this was the invoke agent span earlier I asked
it about like Seattle and Berlin and the city router
kind of decided to route this to like the Bangalore
and the Seattle agent.
And then you can see it invoke the Seattle specialist
to get all the details about Seattle and then goes
back into the copilot fall back for our Berlin related
data.
Yeah, that is super cool.
And to recap, right, So here is a bird's eye
view of what has just happened.
It's actually the next slide.
Yeah.
So what we saw from the playground is that a
user asked a question to the orchestrator and the orchestrator
runs in a foundry hosted agent.
That's kind of the pro code agent that will talk
a little bit more like in a little bit, right.
But that agent serves as orchestrator and route the question
to the right sub agent that is the specialist of
that specific city.
And you can see that each sub agent is running
on a different cloud running with different agent framework.
But because of all of them are emitting open telemetry
traces, Foundry observability was able to stitch together the end
to end execution and put everything in one uniform unified
trace.
And and that's why, like even though they are running
across multiple clouds, it feels like everything is in one
system.
OK, yeah, now let's talk about the key ingredients that
made this possible.
OK, first is Microsoft's agent platform.
We showcase like a foundry agent, foundry prompt agent, right?
That's the no code agents I demoed at the beginning
of the talk.
And Foundry also has like hosted agent, that's our orchestrator
agent.
That's the pro code.
You submit your code or your container to Foundry and
Foundry helps you to manage that and run your code
right so that we have full control of the agent
behavior.
And Foundry's hosted agent is what really shines for enterprise
scenarios because it has enterprise grade VM isolation.
It has agent identity that from Ontree that really guarantees
security and it has like key features like long running
operation routines, right, that are all like no very nice
features for enterprise customers.
But you know, like pro code or no code, I
think it's up to you.
But like foundry got to cover like you can choose
another one that fits your needs, right?
And once you have that, you can have the your
agent built in GitHub with code and prompt check in
to GitHub right?
You can run your agent in Foundry with beauty in
observability, evaluation and optimization.
And once you are ready, you can distribute your agents
to users on M-65.
The second ingredient is open telemetry is Gen.
AI Semantic conventions.
Think of this as a common telemetry schema across frameworks.
Whether it's the Foundry Prompt agent, a land graph app,
or an ADK service, they emit spans with consistent attributes
for agent names, model calls, and key events.
That consistency gives you a strong compatibility with downstream observability
and evaluation features on Microsoft Foundry.
Microsoft heavily contributes to the standards and we actively add
new scenarios to support.
Yeah, that sounds great.
Now, Kumar, can you show us what code change that
you need to make to adopt open telemetry instrumentation?
So Microsoft Open Telemetry Distro is the unified SDK that
can instrument most agent frameworks in multiple programming languages.
Foundry native agents have Microsoft Open Telemetry Distro instrumentation built
in, so I didn't have to make any code changes.
But for agents outside of Foundry, the distro supports auto
instrumentation and it's just a few lines of initialization code
to set up the SDK.
Let me hop on over to VS Code.
So this is my agent and all I have to
do is say use open telemetry and enable using it
with Azure Monitor and pass the Azure Monitor connection string,
tell it what framework I'm using and give it the
agent ID.
This is the same agent ID that I used to
register the agent on Foundry so it can pull up
the traces and correlate them.
Yeah, great.
One thing to call here is that Foundry Observability is
powered by Azure Monitor and Azure Application Insights, right?
And all of the foundry's traces are stored in Azure
Monitor.
So if you are an existing Azure Monitor users, maybe
for like other part of your nonagentic workflows and architecture,
you can keep using existing Azure Monitor features that you
might be already familiar with.
Cool.
Now that we will see unified traces from O3 clouds,
let's talk about why this matters in production, right?
Because, you know, seeing all the traces is great, but
the real value is operational that you want to, you
know, debug issues and monitor patterns and evaluate quality in
one workflow.
So traces are only useful if they can answer questions
quickly, right?
In production and for example like questions people may want
to ask in the demo setup we had is you
know did the routing agent route the question to the
right sub agents right?
Did the retrieval return like weak contacts that might have
caused hallucination problem or maybe like the did the latency
come from a cold start network, slow network or the
model itself?
And over time, we want to probably monitor if there's
any trend that the agent behavior is shifting.
We touched based on debug ability earlier in the talk.
Let me show you how the Monitor tab works.
Here you can see the live traffic patterns, latency distribution
and a few evaluation results.
One of the interesting things is the estimated cost, the
total token usage, the type of evaluations which ran on
the agent scheduled evals.
There were a few and then scheduled red teams as
well.
If we Scroll down, you can see some operational metrics
and one of the things I noticed is the error
rate went up earlier.
I should probably should get that checked out.
And if you keep scrolling down, you can see more
scheduled evaluation results and what the human evaluator did on
this as well.
Yeah, one of the tool called Successes also went down
recently.
I guess we should take a look at it soon.
OK, now let's take a look at the fleet wheel.
On the Operate tab, you can look at all your
agents in a particular Foundry project and take a look
at everything that pops up.
One of the things you can see is our Active
Alerts Foundry.
If you have an agent on Foundry, by default you
have a security workflow running, so you get alerts on,
you know, things like malicious URLs were detected or a
jailbreak attempt was made on your prompt and things like
that.
You can also set up alerts on evaluation results.
So let's say your agent stops working the way it's
supposed to do.
Then you can be alerted on it and you can
see things like agent success rate, agent volume, which was
the most used volume agent over time, and so on.
Yeah, that's very cool.
Definitely feel more confident in production operations with low small
interviews.
Now maybe let's talk about evaluation.
Yeah.
So for evaluations, let me pull up some code that
I wrote.
You can set up evaluations on traces using the Foundry
project line and select what evaluator you want to add
into the testing criteria.
Here I have intent resolution evaluator, and then we run
this on a particular agent ID.
So once you set this up and create an eval,
you get to see eval results which kind of look
like this.
So this one ran a bunch of different metrics, and
I can see that there was some trace which didn't
work well.
So I'll click on this trace and we'll be directly
taken into the trace view of that particular agent.
And once you click on it, you'll be able to
identify what went wrong.
The first thing that I want to see is oh,
this was a the users intent was to compare Bengaluru
and Barcelona for an after work evening and keeping the
plan concise.
But when I see the eval results which show up
here and the task adherence was when we saw the
failure.
So the user asked for a concise comparison, but the
response material did not cover both cities and hence the
task adherence came out to be a failure.
Let's see what the response was.
Well, yeah, there is no comparison.
There is description about both of them.
I guess the evaluator was looking for a table.
Yeah, that's pretty cool.
And yeah, so the the loop we want to draw
here is very simple, right?
Like instrument your code with open telemetry, debug, evaluate and
optimize in production with live traffic and then like again
fleet level visibility if you want to manage and control
them and everything are done on like 1 observability plane.
OK, cool.
And like there are like so many great foundry features
that we cannot cover due to like time constraints in
this session, but want to call out on them so
that you guys can check out check on them later.
So rubric evaluators like creates customized evaluation plan tailored to
your agent, right?
So that solves your evaluation code start problem.
Agent optimization improves your agent by you know, fine tuning
your system prompt, trying out the different models and maybe
leveraging like a few new tools for customers who want
to leverage or opt in for 865.
Foundry natively supports that.
And as much as we like and support and recommend
open telemetry is generative in AI semantic conversions, we understand
like some customers might be using another trace format today
and may not be easy for them to switch.
That's why we want to meet customers where they are.
So we support these two popular frameworks, popular format open
inference and open elementary for like trace viewing and trace
evaluation.
Exactly, We recommend you to check out recordings of other
Foundry sessions.
R Wizard Foundry's public documentation.
Here's the QR code that connects to you to our
repo where with all our agents that we had showcased
earlier.
Yeah, that's great.
And we are really proud of the breadth and depth
of what Foundry has to offer to help you to
run consistent, high quality and actionable of agent observability, right
and build what you want, run it where you need
and observe it all in one place, any agent, any
cloud, one observability plane.
Thank you.